you need to take care of.
The first is this first line here
which is sort of an initialization of this loop counter
and the second is this line here
which is incrementing your loop counter.
The reason why the second one's important
is because let's look at our condition here.
So while n is less than five.
If you didn't have this line here
you would never increment n.
So every time through the loop you'd just keep
printing zeros okay and you'd have an infinite loop.
I do want to show though what if you do have
an infinite loop it's not the end of the world.
So I can say something like so while true print zero.
So this is going to give me an infinite loop
in my program and whoop, okay.
So notice it's just printing the letter p
over and over again and if I let it go any longer
it's gonna slow down the computer.
So I'm gonna hit control C or command C maybe
and it's going to stop the program from printing okay.
So just in case you ever enter infinite loops
in your programs just go to the console
and hit control C and that's going to stop it
from sort of slowing down the computer.
Okay so going back to this example
I was saying that if you're using
counters or variables in order to sort of count up
inside the while loop you have to take care
to initialize a counter variable first
and then to increment it.
Otherwise you'll enter an infinite loop.
That feels a little bit tedious
and so there's a shortcut for doing that exact same thing.
So these four lines you can rewrite those
into these two lines right here
using this new type of loop called a for loop.
So the for loop says for some loop variable
in this case I named it n you can name it whatever you want.
In range five we're going to come back
to what range means in a little bit print n.
So every time through the loop you're going to print out
what the value of n is.
Range five actually creates internally
a sequence of numbers starting from zero
and going to that number five minus one.
So the sequence is going to be zero, one, two, three and four.
The first time through the loop you're going to say
n is equal to zero or internally this is what happens
n gets the value zero you're going to print n.
Then you're going to go back to the top
n gets the value one then you're going to go
execute whatever's inside so you're going to print one.
Then you're going to increment that
to the next value in the sequence
you're going to print out two and so on.
So this is the general look of a for loop.
So we have for some loop variable again
can be named whatever you want in range some number
do a bunch of stuff and again
these are part of this for loop code block
so you should indent them to tell Python
that these are the things that you should do.
So when you're using range some number
you start out with variable getting the value zero.
With variable having value zero
you're going to execute all of these expressions.
After all the expressions in the code block are done
you're going to go on to the next value so one.
You're going to execute all these expressions
with variable being value one and then so on and so on
until you go to sum num minus one.
So using range in that way is a little bit constraining
because you're always going to get values starting from zero
and ending at sum num minus one.
Whatever's in the parentheses in range.
Sometimes you might want to write programs
that maybe start at a custom value.
Don't start at zero maybe they start at five
maybe it started minus ten.
And sometimes you might want to write programs
that don't go with don't increment
the numbers by one but maybe skip every other number
or go every two numbers every three numbers and so on.
So you can customize range to your needs.
The one thing you do need to give it is the stop.
So if you give it only one value in the parentheses
that stands for stop.
And by default start is going to have the value zero